what i'm trying to do is get bounce back
india or bounce back bharath stories
and as far as india inc is concerned uh
foremost to my mind is executive
director of ics lombard sanjiv mantri
simply because of the way that he's he's
been so reactive proactive
and got
his employees and himself
back on their feet in double quick time
and that's what i mean by perfect
synergy hi good morning great to see you
as always and
you're very comfortable in a back in
office so the well-oiled machine of icsa
lombard continues to roll on how are you
doing
uh pleasure meeting you rishi i think
it's been a while since we have
connected and truly blessed to get to
meet up with you go virtually again uh
hope to meet up in your studio pretty
soon uh yes we are back in office uh
almost for a month and a half and
thereabouts and truly
feel that this is the way to operate you
know by while there was a lot of hybrid
stuff which was there we've been on and
off a lot of things have happened but
frankly speaking nothing beats being in
office you know and interacting with
real people in real manner there is
there is some value to it and what the
last probably 18 months have shown a lot
of gratitude
to the fact that something which we had
taken for granted was taken away and now
we can value this a lot more
wonderful i want to know about your
personal bounce back story as well as
the employees
uh there obviously has to be a lot of
planning as far as that is concerned uh
helping the employees get vaccinated you
know yourself in the family to get
vaccinated
and getting back on your feet very very
quickly let's cover that before we get
into uh you know more acquisitions and
other data
no absolutely so it's see the fall which
happened you know sometime in march in
2020 it was a very steep one the the
lockdown came out very sharply
prior to that it was all happening in a
distant country in china and we were
we're just wondering how do you lock
down the city ohana when it got locked
down but from there on the
the impact was pretty fast and before we
knew it by march 22nd 23rd india was in
the lockdown we were all caught very
unaware and we
and some of the jobs were very
intricately linked like call centers and
all you know the the the
team at call center we're not even
having a proper equipment to operate
from home but the way we could turn
around the way our technology team could
come into play in real time solutioning
could happen so that we we don't end up
impacting the customers
was something to really
cherish
i do believe that it took probably two
to three weeks but the new norm became
the way of life for next three to six
months which i would believe also gets
to the
ability of each individual because the
crisis you know this was very strange
right it was individual families society
and then the whole expansion happened
and so there was a corporate entity like
icici lombard we've been very very
proactively engaging with our thing we
opened call centers even they have
challenges if they were mental
challenges they could call and we we
called that santulan and we said please
reach out and talk so that we can solve
those issues because that sometimes the
physical part can be seen and taken care
of but the mental part at times is hard
to you know manage and you end up
suffering a lot more than required so a
lot of those initiatives were taken we
created a lot of digital engagement
initiatives we used to have get together
the way we used to have it
uh you know in the times when things
were normal in a physical manner uh we
created hobby groups within our
employees so that they could connect and
you know talk to each other and inspire
each other to do the best so that's what
we did at the official level at the
personal level yes you know i am a
pretty reasonably you know physically
worked out driven guy i'm not someone
who believes in
you know doing jobs indoor or doing
workouts indoors so there was a steep
form we were all locked into our houses
but uh
i could you know strangely enough find
stairs as a very good way to exercise so
i started using the stairs
outside my house and that became a way
of life the two to three workouts were
put on the steer side and eventually
some bit of gym equipments came in
in the house and we managed our mini gym
to do something or the other was some
physical thing was required
i wouldn't say it was easy but then you
adapted and moved on and made the best
of what you could have at that point of
time wonderful and you must appreciate
that wimbledon as well as u.s open now
had
you know crowds coming in and
it's wonderful to see even in the
cricket uh the ipl stands slowly filling
up in the uae so you know there is a
sense of normalcy to even spot and uh
that's something we can really really
feed off i want to come to now india's
awareness as far as health is concerned
i'll give you a classic example sanjiv
our domestic staff we try and do a
little bit
you know we will tell the maid we'll
take care of your one child's education
but whenever we have tried to approach
medical insurance they've been like
why don't you just give us that amount
in cash instead of getting insurance
because there was no awareness or you
know their perception of wanting to get
medical insurance but i'm finally
pleased to know that you know the the
domestic staff is now coming to my wife
and me and saying that you know after
this pandemic
maybe you know i'll take up your offer
of doing a small medical insurance for
me and that must make you very happy the
role played by the insurance india
industry in india is bouncing back the
backdrop of healthcare initiatives i
think let's talk about that and this
increased awareness of middle class
india
and you know the underprivileged section
of society as far as healthcare is
concerned
so absolutely you've been spot on and
what you've said
we've seen overall uh the health sector
itself has been stretched if i have to
put some basic you know stats into
perspective we've got about a country
about 2 million banks you know for a
country of 1.3 billion population
if we have
only so many private and public bed
available for hospitalization it's a big
challenge and you've got doctors with
just about a million so we're talking
about one doctor four thousand five
hundred and a pandemic of this magnitude
where percentage of population is
getting impacted we all could feel the
stretch you know and it's not about who
has access who has not got access some
total medical
part i think it's required by each and
every citizen come what may so we've
seen temporary stadium getting converted
into hospitals
temporary hospitals getting done in
10-15 days so when there is will there
is way and we could see how india is a
country or healthcare sector in itself
was you know resilient and could think
on the feet and create these things my
only personal belief is i hope we
realize uh what kind of an exchange
exigency can this be and this would
become a norm rather than being done in
an exceptional manner with this this
kind of stuff i think you also made a
very critical point that when it comes
to health insurance per se
we have always said that there are two
things which are important one is
awareness and the second is ability
awareness is a function of how do you
learn how do you reach out to the
insurance sector also has been doing
multiple things
to make you know the the customer aware
that they should take this cover it's
not about taking it from ics lombard
come what may you should have an
insurance cover that's where i come from
and
that's a must in fact i maintain to all
the partners who work on the health
insurance side that if you give health
insurance to a family or give the cover
you're doing a noble deed it's not about
a state it's a service you're doing to
the family because in the need
it will really help every year maybe
almost you know
100 million
individuals and maybe 25 you know
million families go below poverty line
on account of medical exigency and the
current times where the income was
constrained which is where the ability
comes in it would have got further
impacted that's where insurance could
have stepped in and made you live live
your life normally while the expense of
the medical part goes through and that
being said you know in a way the
pandemic has done one very critical
transformation the awareness has got
heightened as you said
you know the helpers at home who are
doing a lot for us and we owe that to
them have realized that we need to take
it this conversation of cash versus
cover which they believe could never be
used has kind of got dissolved because
it's it's happened to everybody spread
you know everywhere but now this
awareness has also done one more thing a
lot of even higher class the penetration
of insurance in the country is less than
four percent rishi to me that's a very
very low percent and this i'm talking
about the recent numbers it's not that
i'm talking once upon a time
so clearly the
the awareness coming into things the
ability
issue will continue but the fact of the
matter is now they've started realizing
that this product this this particular
solution is an investment and not an
expense
some of us have to buy health insurance
in the past because we used to get
benefit on the income tax side they
would allow you as induction and you'll
get that benefit now all of those things
have
changed people want to know the features
of the product people want to know what
are the services that i can get if i get
hospitalized the discussions have become
involved this journey from expense to
insurance becoming an investment is one
of the most critical transformation that
has happened and that is why we are
seeing a significant surge in last 12 to
18 months
this journey hopefully will continue i'm
saying at an official level of course we
do provide solutions and products which
are benefiting but this one is a one
significant transformation
yeah i know that it's not very important
always to be reactive to
something particular which happens in a
country or in the world
for example you need to have a large
product structure which just covers
people for whatever exigencies or
contingencies that come about but
covetous is a unique situation we never
knew something like this could ever
happen to us and what i like is that
icsa lombard was very quick in terms of
of
of providing solutions which are very
covid friendly
i'd like you to address that a bit yeah
no absolutely so
in a very early phase when
this particular pandemic came into play
you know from the few changes that we
did was we
uh we created some features which were
as rightly put across covet friendly
when you buy a policy
there's a cooling period that for 30
days you cannot make claims we said no i
mean a person can get impacted by kovac
we reduce that period to almost 15 days
you said better that obviously you
shouldn't buy it once you've got the
kovit you cannot get the cover but
otherwise if after 15 it will get ready
another thing we realize is because of
pandemic
people will get impacted in a far deeper
way and
the claims will come in and there is a
bonus available if you don't make a
claim in terms of some insured getting
increased we said if you get proved your
some insured bonus will not get impacted
you will still get that so we're giving
an exemption to this last but not the
least one of the most significant
challenges that we had seen in poverty
was that people reluctance to go to the
hospitals for treatment which is outside
just because there doesn't mean other
ailments were not existing there were
other challenges which were still there
people could still get viral could get
typhoid and all of that stuff so they
could be but the reluctance and lit and
pushing the thing off showing showing it
to a doctor was very high we said we'll
start home care
we will make sure that as an insurer
will help you will guide you with the
network or hospital that we operate with
and if something that can be cured at
home
we will get those services to your house
and needless to say we will even pay for
it so these were the few
changes that we did with the simple
aspect that we need to ensure another
thing which we did very very extensively
was giving you telemedicine you know
your access to doctor the best of the
best was made available the volumes have
should have
shot the roof in terms of people
accessing this previously
in the mindset of the customer including
myself i am no different from others we
wanted to see a doctor physically we
were not comfortable accessing him
in a in a remote manner but now we are
able to connect do a video call explain
symptoms and get treatment from the best
of the best and somewhere or the other
it has also released a lot of bandwidth
where doctors can meet more patients and
do what is required to you know solve
the issue so there is a significant
amount of you know uh tech role that
technology also has played to help us
make
access to medicine or the best of the
medicine to the
to the masses at a very consistent in a
very consistent manner
great i was just thinking we've had such
a wonderful association over the years
but there's one thing that we've never
talked about it's m a mergers and
acquisitions so this is going to be a
first and it gives me great joy and
great pleasure to talk to you about this
uh the recent bharti axa acquisition by
icsya lombard let's have your thoughts
on that and uh you know i think it is
consolidation is a wonderful wonderful
step for this industry and this kind of
an m a is what is needed
uh yeah i think
the larger picture was just there are
quite a few players there in the gi
sector and a little bit of consolidation
can always help but to be very honest uh
we are very we're very keen we like the
you know what bhati aksar has been doing
and we are truly blessed and excited to
have the team members becoming part of
ics and lombard as one unit we do
believe that we are better together in
fact that has been the communication
that we have been doing we don't you
want to use size as an advantage
to do lot better for our customers our
clients and reach out to as many as
possible the whole the whole
logic is that with this kind of an
approach we would be able to service and
sharpen everything we don't on reaching
out customers servicing them or also
probably using technological tools uh
which are required which are like aimi
based chat bots whatever's required all
of those excesses will be provided and
we would we you we would be better
stronger in terms of delivering what our
own uh
objective has been from day one
great
we're just a few days away from world
heart day
and it irks me and i'm sure it hurts you
too that india is still called the
diabetes capital of the world
uh heart health is so poor in this
country
and that apart from worrying you must
also cause you to act very very strongly
to send out some strong messages for
world hard days and chief yeah i think
absolutely right
there was a time when i has to believe
you know what is the purpose of having
world hard day
particular if you ask me requires care
every single day right it is the most
it's a tiny organ in your body but it
plays the most critical role of keeping
us alive and kicking isn't it
but then i've realized that such days
like yoga day hard day these are the
occasions by which we can make the world
notice it's up to us as an individual
how we ought to practice every right we
don't uh so these are the times we've
been as a company being in the business
of health and you know when we're very
keen to see a fitter india you know we
do believe that
prevention is better than cure and for
that
it is important that
our friends colleagues and everyone
produces rishikesh needs to take those
steps on our everyday the irony of
keeping ourselves fit is you know it's
something which is known to us to each
one of us but uh
we always wait for tomorrow to make
things happen and that at
times can prove all fatal you know and
there are and see it's not one should
fit all some each one of us will have
different passions the whole
idea is to use that to make things work
out if you are not a gym person i would
just recommend don't go to gym but go
for a walk it doesn't matter you know if
you believe you can swim and that's what
you like do that but you must make sure
that uh you make your you know you make
your heart to use these are the same way
use it or lose it clearly you know
you're better off using it so that you
can create longevity and you can create
a fitter life for yourself there are and
there's some people who are unfortunate
in terms of you know
they may have some inherent challenges
there are cures available there are
solutions available and worst inverse if
it is required and there's a challenge
there are of course insurance which is
there to address the need but you must
put in your
effort on the right side to do
solutioning which is appropriate and to
me my personal message would be don't
wait for tomorrow probably start today
and make sure that you keep your heart
live and kicking all the time
super message
you've been a pioneer in terms of
getting employees to engage with sports
people
and some of the finest sports people in
the world have come
and you know addressed employees you've
got them to engage
uh
also because of your primary passion
which is sport
and what a year we've had sanjeev i mean
if you look at our performance in the
paralympics if you look at our
performance in the olympics
and it must please you a lot
that
nina chopra goes and wins that goal in
the javelin
hockey teams both on the men's and the
women's side doing so well
the boxers
the shooters and of course the
incredible paralympians let's talk about
that
i think
in the current times sports as
an industry was the first one to come
back in action and uh clearly
it's amazing right olympics which takes
uh which takes probably once in four
years and and so many sports on every
four years bracket end up making the
last hurrah the olympics and then they
retire for code all of them have to
postpone continued trainings and the the
preparation the goal the the the effort
i think it's it's it's a it's amazing to
see uh what they go through and the
comeback trail and the performance of
india as a unit you know we've got used
to
uh typically picking up
you know one or two here and there and
that's about it this turned out to be
the best effort for us as a country and
i think nira chopra's effort uh has
transformed athletics for india forever
i remember similar thing happening
to you know in many ways to cricket in
1983 world cup then you had badminton
going through a similar you know
space where we had major people end up
taking that as a sport and you see the
quality of sportsman which has started
coming the level has changed completely
the athletics movement i mean great you
know mr milka seems i wish he was there
to see india actually getting a goal in
the stadium at that point of time we've
all lived with the regrets of pt usha
missing it on the 100th of a second so
rishi for me personally it was truly
amazing you know and at the same time
sports can be a regular you you could
see djokovic not picking up the gold to
get the golden slam in place so
the irony of life continues and then he
went on to even lose the u.s open so he
could not pick up all four of the slams
also but that is life you know that's
that's what is exciting and
i'm i
feel truly blessed
to see that uh
sports was the first one to you know
come back into normal stream and now
with people in the stadium as you said
again
we see good times ahead for all of us
lovely icsr lombard gic
please find them on social media whether
it's uh twitter facebook instagram or
linkedin and follow them sanjiva sanjeev
mantri s a n j double e v mantri uh you
can follow him on linkedin on twitter as
well as instagram
listen uh conversations with you are an
absolute pleasure
thank you for speaking to me about your
bounce back story and i wish uh icicial
over gic all the best on their excellent
leadership
thank you so much rishike and hopefully
look forward to seeing you soon in
person and pleasure pleasure always a
pleasure being on
on chat with you thank you